Guide to the Genrikh Markovich Deĭch Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Genrikh Markovich Deĭch papers
1989-1992
MS 1599
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
1
(2 boxes)
The papers consist of correspondence, writings, and research notes relating to Aleksandr Pushkin, V. I. Lenin, and the town of Liubavich. Also included are materials for a guidebook to Jewish activities and documents preserved in the archives of the government of Tsarist Russia.
Deĭch, G. M. (Genrikh Markovich)
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Received from Genrikh Markovich Deĭch, 1990 and 1992.
Scope and Contents
The Genrikh Markovich Deĭch Papers consist of materials written and collected by Deĭch, Soviet citizen and official biographer of Lenin. The majority of the papers pertain to Aleksandr Pushkin (1799-1837), poet and prose writer, and to Vladimir Ilyich Lenin (1870-1924), founder of Bolshevism and Soviet leader from 1917-1924.
Materials for a guidebook to Jewish documents preserved in Russian archives (18th-20th centuries) are included in the collection as well as historical background of the town of Liubavich.
The papers, received from Genrikh Markovich Deĭch in 1990, are in Russian; only folder titles have been translated.
Conditions Governing Access
The collection is open for research.
Jews -- Russia; Deĭch, G. M. (Genrikh Markovich); Lenin, Vladimir Ilʹich, 1870-1924; Pushkin, Aleksandr Sergeevich, 1799-1837
- Inventory
  Scope and Contents
  The Genrikh Markovich Deĭch Papers are in Russian; only folder titles have been translated into English.
  - "Autobiography", 1990 February 17 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Documents and commentary attesting to the Jewish origin of V.I. Lenin, 1846 October 12, 1992 September 26 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - "Governors' accounts from the 1840s-1860s as source for the calculating of European Russia's non-Russian Orthodox population"
    - Draft of article (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Rejection of article by Soviet Ethnography (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - "Leniniana: 1. Manuscript of the book Lenin's Portrait Sketches of his Friends and Opponents" (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Research materials (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - "Leniniana: 6. Leniniana in journals" (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - "Leniniana: 8. V.I. Lenin and musuems" (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - "Leniniana: 9. Reviews of my work" (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Leniniana: correspondence and notes pertaining to publications (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - "Letters to I. F. Armand" (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - List of Scholarly works by G. M. Deĭch through February 1989 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - "V. I. Lenin and G. E. Zinoviev" (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - "V. I. Lenin and L. B. Kamenev" (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - "V. I. Lenin and N. I. Bukharin": article and review, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - "V. I. Lenin and P. B. Aksel'rod" (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - "V. I. Lenin and V. I. Zasulich" (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - "Vladmir Il'ich Lenin and Ivan Vasil'evich Babushkin" (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - "Materials for a guidebook to Jewish activities and documents preserved in the archives of the supreme and central government of Tsarist Russia, 18th-20th centuries"
    - "Part 1: 43-page typewritten text (through first interval)" (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - "Part 2: 56-page typewritten guidebook (through second interval); includes subject index; this version seems not to include all the archives, but this would have to be verified" (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - "Part 3: Combined register of the guidebooks information (mine); from the guidebook for the TsGIAL published in 1956" (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - "Part 4: 65-page rough draft for the preceding work" (not all 65 pages are present) (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - "Part 5: Handwritten notes about the guidebook" (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - "Pushkin materials: 1. Uncompleted articles about Pushkin" (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - "Pushkin materials: 2. Correspondence with the director of the Pskov archive, G.R. Rafel'son about the Pushkin materials in the archive (file)" (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - "Pushkin materials: 3. Copies of archival documents about Pushkin, the publication in the journal Russian Literature of which it has been proposed, and correspondence about this" (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - "Pushkin materials: 4. List of some archives of the TsGIA of the USSR in which materials about Pushkin have appeared" (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - "Pushkin materials: 5. Photographs of documents about Pushkin" (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - "Studies on the history of the town of Liubavich": draft of article (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - "Studies on the history of the town of Liubavich": photographs of documents (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - "Studies on the history of the town of Liubavich": photographs of plans of the town (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - "Studies on the history of the town of Liubavich": research materials (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence pertaining to publications (Box 2, Folder 33)